As you can see on this slide, today, we
이 슬라이드에서
are going to talk about neural networks and backpropagation.
보시다시피, 오늘 우리는 신경망과 역전파에 대해 이야기할 것입니다.
Which is actually the process--
사실 이는 초기 시절에
early years, I was studying this,
제가 공부하던 과정으로,
I was often referring to it as the magical process that
신경망이 자신의 실수로부터 배우게 해주는 마법
lets the neural networks learn from their own mistakes,
같은 과정이라고 자주 언급했습니다.
pretty much like humans but in a more organized fashion,
인간과 비슷하지만 더 조직적인 방식으로,
and also using a little bit more math.
그리고 약간의 수학을 사용합니다.
So let's dive into the topic.
그럼 주제로 들어가 보겠습니다.
I'm sure this is going to be exciting.
이것이 흥미로울 것이라고 확신합니다.
And this is laying the foundation
그리고 이것은 이번 분기의 나머지 부분을 위한
for the rest of the quarter.
기초를 다지는 것입니다.
Every single algorithm that we will be discussing in the future
앞으로 논의할 모든 알고리즘은
without even mentioning is using a form of backpropagation.
언급하지 않더라도 역전파의 형태를 사용하고 있습니다.
And so that's why understanding this lecture and the topics
그래서 이 강의와 주제를 이해하는 것이 매우
is very important.
중요합니다.
OK, in keeping us with the tradition,
좋습니다, 전통을 이어가며
let's cover what we've talked about so far.
지금까지 이야기한 내용을 정리해 보겠습니다.
So I'm sure you now remember what we talked about last time.
이제 지난 시간에 이야기한 내용을 기억하고 계실 것이라고 확신합니다.
We said, how we can form the objective functions, or loss
우리는 목표 함수 또는 손실 함수, 우리가 여기서 부르는 것을 어떻게 형성할 수 있는지에
functions, what we call here.
대해 이야기했습니다.
And then we talked about regularization.
그리고 정규화에 대해서도 이야기했습니다.
But to do that, we formulated everything
그것을 위해 우리는 모든 것을 x,
through the x, y, defining the pairs and a scoring function.
y를 통해 공식화하고, 쌍과 점수 함수를 정의했습니다.
Which, in this case, we are using a linear scoring function,
이 경우 우리는 선형 점수 함수를
as you can see, and also defining,
사용하고 있으며, 궁극적으로 이 손실 함수를
ultimately, this loss function.
정의하고 있습니다.
So this graph that you see on the right
오른쪽에 보이는
is what we drew, showing all the process, the entire process
이 그래프는 우리가 그린 것으로, 학습의 전체 과정을
of learning.
보여줍니다.
There has been some questions.
몇 가지 질문이 있었습니다.
Questions in the last lecture and also even before that,
지난 강의와 그 이전에도 왜 우리가 소프트맥스 함수만
that why we are only using the softmax function.
사용하는지에 대한 질문이 있었습니다.
I wanted to reiterate that it's not the only loss function
이것이 우리가 가지고 있는 유일한 손실 함수가 아니며, 우리가
that we have and we use.
사용하는 것임을 다시 강조하고 싶습니다.
It's one of the most widely used in deep learning and building,
이는 딥러닝과 특히 분류 작업을 위한 구축에서 가장 널리
especially for the task of classification.
사용되는 것 중 하나입니다.
But there are so many other options
하지만 다른 작업을 위해 사용하는
that we use for other tasks, for different tasks.
많은 다른 옵션이 있습니다.
Even for the task of classification,
분류 작업의 경우, 우리가
if you've looked at the slides that we've
웹사이트에 공유한
shared on the website, I included this hinge loss,
슬라이드를 보셨다면, 강의 2의 읽기
or used to be called SVM loss in the reading
과제에서 힌지 손실 또는 이전에 SVM 손실이라고 불리던
assignments in lecture two.
것을 포함했습니다.
So in the slides, we had examples and everything
슬라이드에는 힌지 손실 주제에
around the topic of hinge loss.
대한 예시와 모든 것이 포함되어 있었습니다.
It is also one of those widely used loss
이는 특히 신경망의 초기 시절에
functions, especially in the early years of neural networks.
널리 사용된 손실 함수 중 하나입니다.
And just to give you a high level understanding of what
그것이 무엇인지에 대한 높은 수준의 이해를
it is, this is a loss function, that unlike softmax, does not
제공하기 위해, 이는 소프트맥스와 달리 점수를 확률로 변환하지
turn the scores into probabilities.
않는 손실 함수입니다.
So turning them into probabilities
따라서 점수를 확률로 변환하는
is not the only option.
것이 유일한 옵션은 아닙니다.
So we can use other forms.
다른 형태를 사용할 수 있습니다.
This function encourages the score of--
이 함수는 Syi로
let me highlight here--
정의된 올바른
the score of the correct items, which
항목의 점수가 모든 다른
is defined by Syi to be higher than the scores
항목 Sj의 점수보다 높도록
of all other items Sj.
장려합니다.
You can see the condition here, creating a value of 0
여기 조건을 보실 수 있으며, 조건이 참일 경우 0의
if the condition is true.
값을 생성합니다.
And otherwise, what it does is--
그렇지 않으면, 제가 말한 대로,
so as I said, it encourages the score of the correct item
올바른 항목의 점수가 모든 다른 항목의 점수보다
to be higher than the scores of all other items
최소한의 여유를 두고 높아지도록
by at least a margin.
장려합니다.
That number one that you see there
여기 보이는 숫자
is the margin that it creates.
1은 생성된 여유입니다.
And then if the condition is violated,
그리고 조건이 위반되면
the loss increases proportionally from the margin.
손실은 여유에서 비례적으로 증가합니다.
And this is the visualization-- so
그리고
creating this visualization of the function.
이것은 함수의 시각화입니다.
So this promotes correct scores by penalizing cases,
따라서 이는 관련 없는 항목이 너무 높은 점수를 받을 경우
where irrelevant items are scored too highly.
벌점을 부여하여 올바른 점수를 촉진합니다.
So again, refer to reading assignment in lecture two
다시 말해, 예제와 더 나은 이해를
for examples and to get better understanding of that.
위해 강의 2의 읽기 과제를 참조하세요.
Next, we have talked about general optimization,
다음으로, 우리는 일반 최적화에 대해
how to find the best parameters, W, for the neural network.
이야기했으며, 신경망의 최적 매개변수 W를 찾는 방법에 대해 논의했습니다.
And in doing so, we talked a little bit
그 과정에서 우리는 이
about this loss landscape being as a large valley as shown
이미지에 나타난 것처럼 손실 경관이 큰 계곡과 같다는 것에 대해
in this image.
조금 이야기했습니다.
And every point on that valley is a different set
그 계곡의 모든 점은 서로 다른 가중치
of weight parameters.
매개변수 집합입니다.
And we wanted to find the set of parameters, W, that
우리는 그 손실 경관을 최소화하는
minimizes that loss landscape.
매개변수 집합 W를 찾고자 했습니다.
We talked about the fact that the key
우리는 손실 함수
is being able to take the gradient of the loss
L의 기울기를 W에 대해 취하고,
function, L, with respect to W and use
이를 단계별로 최적화에 사용하는 것이
the gradient for optimization in a step-by-step manner.
핵심이라는 사실에 대해 이야기했습니다.
Which gave us the gradient descent algorithm.
이로 인해 우리는 경량 하강 알고리즘을 얻었습니다.
So the weights are basically updated.
따라서 가중치는 기본적으로 업데이트됩니다.
Although it's very hard for me to see from this distance,
이 거리에서 내가 가리키고 있는
what I'm pointing to, but I can guess.
것을 보는 것은 매우 어렵지만, 추측할 수 있습니다.
So anyways, in order to walk down
어쨌든 손실 경관을 최소값 쪽으로
the loss landscape towards the minimum value,
내려가기 위해 단계 크기가
a step size is defined and we often
정의되며, 우리는 종종
get to take one step with respect to a step size
기울기의 음의 방향으로 단계 크기에 따라
in the negative direction of the gradient.
한 걸음을 내딛습니다.
So this was the gradient descent algorithm.
그래서 이것이 경량 하강 알고리즘이었습니다.
And in order to optimize, we talked
최적화를 위해 우리는
about two different approaches of numerical gradient
수치적 기울기와 해석적 기울기의 두 가지 접근 방식에
and analytical gradient, both of which having pros and cons.
대해 이야기했으며, 두 가지 모두 장단점이 있습니다.
And we discussed in practice to derive analytical gradients--
우리는 실제로 해석적 기울기를 도출하는 것에
in practice, we derive analytical gradients.
대해 논의했습니다.
And often, if it's hard to do the implementation and the math
그리고 구현과 수학이
and everything, we check our implementations
어렵다면, 우리는
with numerical gradients.
수치적 기울기로 구현을 확인합니다.
And one of the other challenges we talked about
우리가 이야기한 또 다른 도전
was the use of incorporating the loss function and its gradients
과제 중 하나는 전체 데이터 세트에서 손실 함수와 그 기울기를 통합하는
on the entire data set.
것이었습니다.
So if you have a large data set, it's very expensive
따라서 대규모 데이터 세트가 있는 경우,
to run the loss function and the derivative on the entire data
전체 데이터 세트에서 손실 함수와 도함수를 실행하는 것은 매우 비용이 많이
set.
듭니다.
And that's why we talked about the idea of mini batches,
그래서 우리는 데이터 세트에서
using a number of examples sampled from the data set,
샘플링된 여러 예제, 보통 32, 64, 128 또는 256을
often maybe 32, 64, or 128, or 256.
사용하는 미니 배치의 아이디어에 대해 이야기했습니다.
And that subsampled data is used for identifying the gradients
그리고 그 서브샘플링된 데이터는 그래디언트를 식별하고
and then taking the steps towards the minimum.
최소값으로 나아가는 단계를 취하는 데 사용됩니다.
And beyond SGD and stochastic gradient descent,
SGD와 확률적 경량 하강법을 넘어, 우리는
we talked about some optimizations of SGD
모멘텀, RMSProp 및 Adam
with Momentum, RMSProp, and Adam optimizer.
최적화기를 사용한 SGD의 몇 가지 최적화에 대해 이야기했습니다.
And there were a lot of details that I would refer you
그리고 이와 관련된 많은 세부
to the lecture, the third lecture,
사항이 있으며, 특정 질문이
if you have any specific questions about this.
있다면 세 번째 강의를 참조하시기 바랍니다.
And then one of the other things that we
그리고 우리가 이야기한 다른
talked about was the importance of the learning rate
것 중 하나는 학습률의 중요성과
and scheduling the learning rate.
학습률 스케줄링이었습니다.
And in some of the optimizers, we
그리고 일부
often try to start with a larger value of the learning rate
최적화기에서는 보통 더 큰 학습률
and then start using different types of decaying the learning
값으로 시작한 다음 학습률을 감소시키거나
rate, or reducing its value by a factor.
값을 줄이는 다양한 방법을 사용합니다.
And this is normally needed in many optimizers.
이것은 많은 최적화기에서 일반적으로 필요합니다.
But in some of the more recent ones, Adam and its variants,
하지만 최근의 Adam 및 그 변형에서는
we often do not need to manually, or explicitly decrease
수동으로 또는 명시적으로 감소시킬 필요가
that because that is encoded into the optimizer itself.
없으며, 이는 최적화기 자체에 인코딩되어 있습니다.
So with that, I want us to get to the topic of neural networks
그래서 이를 바탕으로 신경망 주제로 넘어가서 실제로
and see how we can actually build neural networks
신경망을 구축하고 더 흥미롭고
and solve more exciting and harder problems.
어려운 문제를 해결하는 방법을 살펴보겠습니다.
So we've so far talked about this function, linear function,
지금까지 우리는 W와 x의 곱인 이 선형 함수에 대해
of W multiplied by x.
이야기했습니다.
And that is the most basic neural network
그리고 이것은 단지 하나의 레이어로 정의될 수
that could be defined as just one layer.
있는 가장 기본적인 신경망입니다.
We will be talking about the layers.
우리는 레이어에 대해 이야기할 것입니다.
And what I want you to pay attention to here
여기서 주목해야 할 것은 입력
are these dimensions D and C, which
데이터의 차원 D와
are the dimensionality of the input data,
C로, 입력 x의 차원
input x, or the number of features.
또는 특성의 수입니다.
And C is the number of classes, basically, the number
C는 클래스의 수,
of outputs, nodes, or neurons, whatever number of outputs
기본적으로 출력의 수, 노드 또는
we need.
뉴런의 수입니다.
And in order to create a neural network at a second layer,
두 번째 레이어에서 신경망을 만들기 위해, 우리는 여기서
we can define a new set of weights referred to as W2 here.
W2라고 하는 새로운 가중치 집합을 정의할 수 있습니다.
And we apply those to the previous layer
그리고 우리는 그것을 W1과 x의
of W1 multiplied by x.
곱인 이전 레이어에 적용합니다.
Again, pay attention to the dimensionalities
다시 말하지만, 여기서 차원에 주목하세요.
here that we have the C number of outputs and D
우리는 C개의 출력과 D개의 입력
as the number of input features.
특성을 가지고 있습니다.
But then you also define H, and that
하지만 H도 정의하고, 이는
defines the number of neurons, the number of hidden layer
뉴런의 수, 은닉층 노드 또는 뉴런의
nodes, or neurons.
수를 정의합니다.
That's one point.
그것이 한 가지 포인트입니다.
The second point is this max function
두 번째 포인트는 우리가
that we'll be coming back to.
다시 돌아올 max 함수입니다.
And we'll explain what it is and what it means.
우리가 그것이 무엇인지, 그리고 그것이 의미하는 바를 설명하겠습니다.
What the max operation is doing here
여기서 max 연산이 하는
is to create a non-linearity between
것은 W1과 W2에 의해 수행된
the linear transformations done by W1 and W2.
선형 변환 사이에 비선형성을 생성하는 것입니다.
And this is actually a very, very important part
그리고 이것은 실제로 과정에서 매우, 매우
of the process.
중요한 부분입니다.
I will talk a little bit about the non-linearity
비선형성에 대해 조금
but also look at this last part before I forget.
이야기하겠지만, 잊기 전에 이 마지막 부분도 살펴보겠습니다.
In practice, that's right that we are only including W and x,
실제로, 우리는 첫 번째와 두 번째 강의에서
as we talked about this in the first and second lecture.
이야기한 것처럼 W와 x만 포함하고 있습니다.
We also incorporate a bias just to have a complete framework.
우리는 완전한 프레임워크를 갖기 위해 바이어스도 포함합니다.
So in practice, we also have bias,
그래서 실제로 우리는
but we don't write it here for the sake of simplicity.
바이어스도 있지만, 단순함을 위해 여기에는 쓰지 않습니다.
Anyways, the max operation is creating the nonlinearity.
어쨌든, max 연산이 비선형성을 생성하고 있습니다.
And it's actually very important because, as we talked
그리고 이것은 실제로 매우
about the linear classifiers in the last few lectures,
중요합니다. 왜냐하면 지난 몇 강의에서 선형 분류기에 대해 이야기했을
we said, we mentioned that there are so many different problems
때, 우리는 샘플을 단일 선으로 분리할
that we can't separate the samples with just
수 없는 다양한 문제가 있다고
one single line.
언급했습니다.
This was one of the examples that in order
이것은 신경망과 선형 함수로 이
to be able to solve this problem with neural networks,
문제를 해결하기 위해 원래
with linear functions, we need some sort of nonlinear
공간에서 새로운 공간으로 비선형
transformation from the original space to a new space.
변환이 필요하다는 예 중 하나였습니다.
And now, in the new space, you see that they are separable,
그리고 이제 새로운 공간에서, 선을 사용하여 분리할 수
using a line.
있음을 알 수 있습니다.
So in this case, it's a nonlinear transformation
따라서 이 경우, 입력과 두 번째 공간 간의 비선형 변환이
between the input and then the second space,
있으며, 이는 x와
which is mapping the x and y to their polar coordinates, r
y를 극좌표 r과 theta로 매핑합니다.
But again, this is just one example.
하지만 다시 말하지만, 이것은 단지 하나의 예일 뿐입니다.
There are so many other examples, too.
다른 많은 예가 있습니다.
So with this example, let's go back to-- oops,
이 예를 가지고, 다시 돌아가서-- 오ops,
let's go back to our definition of the two layer neural network.
다시 두 층 신경망의 정의로 돌아갑니다.
As you've probably seen in the literature
아마도 여러분이 문헌과 이 수업
and outside this class, these types
외부에서 보았듯이, 가중치와
of networks which only depend on weights and inputs and layers
입력, 층에만 의존하는 이러한 유형의 네트워크는 곱셈
and so on, there are no other operations than multiplication,
외에 다른 연산이 없기 때문에 종종
are often referred to as fully connected networks,
완전 연결 네트워크 또는 다층
or multi-layer perceptrons, MLPs.
퍼셉트론(MLP)이라고 불립니다.
So that's one thing.
그래서 그것이 한 가지입니다.
And we can actually stack more and more layers
그리고 우리는 실제로 더
to create better, more larger networks.
많은 층을 쌓아 더 나은, 더 큰 네트워크를 만들 수 있습니다.
And in this case, again, pay attention
그리고 이 경우, 다시
to the dimensionalities and the hidden layers
차원과 중간에
that we have in the middle and the dimensionalities that
있는 은닉층에 주목하고, 차원들이
do match one after the other.
서로 일치하는지 확인하세요.
So back to this visual representation of what
신경망이 무엇을 하는지에 대한 이 시각적
the neural network is doing.
표현으로 돌아갑니다.
We talked about this when we had the linear representations,
우리는 선형 표현을 가질 때 이것에 대해
that often what happens is the network, through the weights,
이야기했으며, 종종 네트워크가 가중치를 통해 어떤 템플릿을
is learning some sort of templates.
학습하는 일이 발생합니다.
If you remember last week, we were
지난 주에 우리가 학습되고 있는 이러한
talking about these templates that are being learned.
템플릿에 대해 이야기했던 것을 기억하십니까?
So again, I'm saying, templates, they're not.
그래서 다시 말하지만, 템플릿이라고 말하고 있습니다. 그렇지만 그것들은 아닙니다.
I mean, they are some representatives of the images
즉, 그것들은 이미지의 대표자이지만, 어떤
but from the data, depending on what data it was trained on.
데이터에 대해 훈련되었는지에 따라 다릅니다.
So these templates in what we discussed last week
그래서 지난 주에 논의한 이러한 템플릿은
were generated by these 10 outputs
입력 뉴런 위에 W를 적용하여 생성된
by applying the W's on top of the input neurons.
10개의 출력에 의해 생성되었습니다.
So with that, now that we have multiple layers, more layers,
그래서 이제 여러 층이 있고, 더 많은 층이 있으므로, 이제 실제로
now we can actually create some more templates.
더 많은 템플릿을 생성할 수 있습니다.
Now, we have a layer in the middle that can actually
이제 우리는 중간에 100개의 템플릿을
create 100 templates, as opposed to just 10
생성할 수 있는 층이 있으며, 이는 선형 분류기에 대해 단지
for a linear classifier.
10개에 해당합니다.
Although we still have those 10 as well.
비록 여전히 그 10개도 가지고 있지만요.
And this, again, in a very high level-- from a very high level
그리고 이것은 다시 매우 높은 수준에서, 매우 높은 수준의 이해
understanding point of view, I'm telling you what this means.
관점에서, 제가 이것이 의미하는 바를 말씀드리고 있습니다.
When we have these 100 neurons in the middle,
중간에 100개의 뉴런이 있을 때, 우리는
we are giving the network the power
네트워크에 전체
to create templates for not entire objects
객체가 아닌 객체의 일부를 위한 템플릿을 생성할
but maybe parts of the object.
수 있는 힘을 주고 있습니다.
For example, the classes that you see here,
예를 들어, 여기 보이는
we had bird, cat, deer, dog, frog, horse, they all have eyes.
클래스는 새, 고양이, 사슴, 개, 개구리, 말이 있으며, 이들은 모두 눈을 가지고 있습니다.
So one of those 10 templates, 100 templates
그래서 그 10개의 템플릿 중 하나,
could probably be a part of the object that could be shared
100개의 템플릿은 아마도 모든 클래스 간에 공유될 수 있는
between all of the classes.
객체의 일부일 수 있습니다.
So from a high level point of view and understanding
따라서 높은 수준의 관점에서
these can form templates.
보면, 이것들이 템플릿을 형성할 수 있습니다.
And when we come back to the topics of visualization
그리고 시각화 주제와 신경망에서 배운
and what we learned from the neural networks, this topic,
것에 대해 돌아오면, 지금 제가 이야기하고
we'll uncover more details about what
있는 것에 대한 더 많은 세부사항을
I'm talking about right now.
밝혀낼 것입니다.
So back to the function max.
그래서 함수 max로 돌아갑니다.
We talked about max function, the nonlinearity
우리는 여기서 생성된 비선형성인 max
that is created here.
함수에 대해 이야기했습니다.
And in neural network terminology,
신경망 용어로 우리는 이를
we call that an activation function.
활성화 함수라고 부릅니다.
And it's actually playing a very, very important role,
그리고 이것은 모델을 구축하고 신경망을
a pivotal role, in building the model,
구축하는 데 매우 중요한 역할을
building a neural network.
하고 있습니다.
Let's answer this question that we have on the slide.
슬라이드에 있는 이 질문에 답해봅시다.
What happens if we try to build a neural network without one
이 활성화 함수 중 하나, 예를 들어 max 함수를 제거하고
of these activation functions, let's say, the max function?
신경망을 구축하려고 하면 어떻게 될까요?
This will be our function if I remove the max.
max를 제거하면 우리의 함수는 이렇게 될 것입니다.
So it would be W2 multiply by W1 by x.
그래서 W2에 W1과 x를 곱한 것입니다.
What would happen here?
여기서 무슨 일이 일어날까요?
Yes, exactly.
네, 정확히 그렇습니다.
So as you can guess and correctly, you mentioned,
당신이 추측할 수 있듯이, W2와
the multiplication of W2 by W1 could actually
W1의 곱셈은 실제로 다른 행렬 W3로
be replaced easily with another matrix, W3.
쉽게 대체될 수 있습니다.
And then your function becomes just a linear function.
그럼 당신의 함수는 단순한 선형 함수가 됩니다.
So everything could be lumped together.
그래서 모든 것이 함께 묶일 수 있습니다.
So we need some sort of non-linearity
따라서 비선형 문제를
in the middle to be able to give us the power
해결할 수 있는 힘을 주기 위해 중간에
to solve non-linear problems.
어떤 비선형성이 필요합니다.
The function that we just talked about is a ReLU.
우리가 방금 이야기한 함수는 ReLU입니다.
It's the rectified linear unit.
이는 정류된 선형 유닛입니다.
It's a very popular function, activation function,
신경망에서 사용되는 매우
used in neural networks.
인기 있는 활성화 함수입니다.
While there are so many other variants that
많은 다른 아키텍처와 더
have been tested in many other architectures
현대적인 아키텍처에서 테스트된 많은
and even in the more modern architectures, one
다른 변형이 있지만, ReLU의
of the problems that ReLU has is,
문제 중 하나는
it sometimes creates dead neurons
때때로 모든 것을 0으로
because it's making everything equal to 0,
만들기 때문에 죽은 뉴런을 생성한다는
if it's not positive.
것입니다.
So in order to avoid the dead neurons, leaky ReLU,
따라서 죽은 뉴런을 피하기 위해, 이 유형의
with this type of modeling, or ELU,
모델링을 사용하는 leaky ReLU
that the exponential linear unit are other options.
또는 지수 선형 유닛인 ELU가 다른 옵션입니다.
ELU is a little bit better because it has a better
ELU는 더 나은 제로 중심
zero-centered function.
함수를 가지고 있기 때문에 조금 더 좋습니다.
And then there are some newer variations, GeLU, Gaussian,
그리고 GeLU, 가우시안 또는 선형 유닛과 같은 몇 가지
or linear unit.
새로운 변형이 있습니다.
Or I don't know, I've heard both variations, ELU and GeLU--
또는 ELU와 GeLU 두 가지 변형을
so could be used.
모두 들어본 적이 있습니다.
They are often used more often in neural architecture
이들은 종종 변환기에서 신경 아키텍처에서 더
in transformers.
자주 사용됩니다.
And we also have SiLU, or switch.
그리고 SiLU 또는 스위치도 있습니다.
It's the sigmoid linear unit that, one,
이는 현대 CNNR 아키텍처 중 일부에서
is also used in some of the modern CNNR architectures.
사용되는 시그모이드 선형 유닛입니다.
Google was using this for some of the variations
구글은 그들의 모델의 일부 변형과
of their models and also in EfficientNet.
EfficientNet에서 이를 사용하고 있었습니다.
Other than these, there are functions like sigmoid and Tanh,
이 외에도 시그모이드와 탄하(Tanh)와
or Tanh that are often also used as activation functions.
같은 함수들이 종종 활성화 함수로 사용됩니다.
Although they do have a few problems
하지만 이들은 값이 좁은 범위로 압축되기
because they do squash values in a narrow range.
때문에 몇 가지 문제가 있습니다.
And that sometimes results in vanishing gradients.
이로 인해 기울기 소실이 발생하기도 합니다.
So we often do not use sigmoid or Tanh
그래서 우리는 종종 신경망의 중간에서
in the middle of the neural networks.
시그모이드나 탄하를 사용하지 않습니다.
They are often used in the later layers, where
이들은 종종 후반 층에서 사용되며, 예를 들어
we want to, for example, binarize the outputs
출력을 이진화하는
and things like that.
등의 작업을 원할 때 사용됩니다.
So as I said, ReLU is often a good default choice.
그래서 제가 말했듯이, ReLU는 종종 좋은 기본 선택입니다.
It's very much used in many architectures.
많은 아키텍처에서 매우 많이 사용됩니다.
And there are so many variations of the same function
우리가 이야기한 동일한
that we talked about.
함수의 변형이 매우 많습니다.
I want to summarize what we've talked about
우리가 이야기한 내용을 요약하고 몇 가지
and then answer some questions.
질문에 답하고 싶습니다.
So we did talk about different adding layers and so on.
우리는 다양한 추가 층에 대해 이야기했습니다.
But I want to highlight that activation functions are often
하지만 활성화 함수는 종종 층에서
functions that are operating in the layers.
작동하는 함수라는 점을 강조하고 싶습니다.
And we also have W's, which define
그리고 우리는 이전 층과 다음
the weights mapping between the previous layer
층 간의 가중치를
and the next layer.
정의하는 W도 있습니다.
Again, these are fully connected neural networks
다시 말해, 이것들은 매우
with very simple implementations.
간단한 구현을 가진 완전 연결 신경망입니다.
What we only need is to be able to define an activation
우리가 필요한 것은 활성화 함수를 정의할 수 있는
function.
것입니다.
And in this example, if you look at the example,
이 예제를 보면,
we have the sigmoid function defined as the activation
활성화 함수로 정의된 시그모이드 함수를
function and very easily using that activation.
쉽게 사용할 수 있습니다.
The first and the second layers of the hidden values,
숨겨진 값, 숨겨진 뉴런의 첫 번째 및
hidden neurons, are calculated by applying W1 by x and then
두 번째 층은 W1을 x에 적용한 다음 바이어스를
also the bias and then applying the function,
추가하고 활성화 함수를 적용하여
the activation function.
계산됩니다.
And then same for H2, and the output
H2에 대해서도
will be very simply the dot product between the W3
동일하게 적용되며, 출력은 W3와 숨겨진 값의 마지막
and the last layer of hidden values,
층 간의 내적이 되어 출력
creating the output layer.
층을 생성합니다.
I'll stop here to answer some questions if there are any.
질문이 있다면 여기서 멈추고 답변하겠습니다.
And then, we'll love to continue it.
그리고 나서 계속 진행하고 싶습니다.
That is a great question.
정말 좋은 질문입니다.
And the question is, how would we
질문은 새로운 문제에 대해
choose for a new problem which of these activation functions
이러한 활성화 함수 중 어떤
to use?
것을 선택할 것인가입니다.
The short answer to your question
질문에 대한 간단한
is yes, it's empirical in most cases.
대답은 대부분의 경우 경험적이라는 것입니다.
But we often start with value, or we
하지만 우리는 종종 값을
go with standard activation functions
시작하거나 특정 아키텍처에 사용되는
being used for those specific architectures.
표준 활성화 함수를 사용합니다.
As I mentioned, there are activation functions
앞서 언급했듯이, CNN이나 변환기
that are often commonly used in CNNs, or in transformers
및 다양한 아키텍처에서 자주 사용되는 활성화
and different architectures.
함수가 있습니다.
So we often go with the ones that are tested before.
그래서 우리는 종종 이전에 테스트된 것들을 선택합니다.
But yes, it's mostly empirical.
하지만 네, 대부분 경험적입니다.
If you're designing a new network for a new problem,
새로운 문제를 위한 새로운 네트워크를 설계하는
then that's one of your choices that you have to make,
경우, 이는 다른 하이퍼파라미터와 매우
very much similar to other hyperparameters.
유사하게 선택해야 할 사항 중 하나입니다.
So the question here is, what is the attribute
그래서 여기서 질문은 이러한 모든 활성화
that is basically common between all of these activation
함수 간의 공통 속성이 무엇이며,
functions and what it really does?
그것이 실제로 무엇을 하는가입니다.
I will give you some examples.
몇 가지 예를 드리겠습니다.
And I'll go into some of the details of what these activation
그리고 이러한 활성화 함수가 무엇을 하는지에
functions are doing.
대한 세부 사항으로 들어가겠습니다.
Basically, the main and the most important common characteristic
기본적으로 여기서 가장 중요하고 공통적인 특징은 비선형성을
here is to create nonlinearity.
생성하는 것입니다.
We're not using a linear function as the activation.
우리는 활성화로 선형 함수를 사용하지 않습니다.
So creating some sort of nonlinearity
비선형성을 만드는
is something that makes it very important.
것은 매우 중요합니다.
And why do we have so many variations?
왜 이렇게 많은 변형이 있을까요?
I told you a little bit about the problems
소실 기울기에 대한 문제를
with vanishing gradients.
조금 말씀드렸습니다.
I told you a little bit about differentiability
함수의 미분 가능성에 대해 조금
of the functions.
말씀드렸습니다.
They should be differentiable because we are using them
신경망에서 사용하기 때문에 미분
in neural network.
가능해야 합니다.
And sometimes, having a proper zero-centered value
적절한 제로 중심 값과 부드러운 함수가 있으면 수렴하는
and a smooth function makes it much faster
네트워크를 더 빠르게
to get converging networks.
얻을 수 있습니다.
So there are so many different factors.
다양한 요인이 많습니다.
These are the main ones that I told you and talked about,
이것들은 제가 말씀드리고 이야기한
which play an important role for defining,
주요 요소들로, 이러한 함수를
or designing these functions.
정의하거나 설계하는 데 중요한 역할을 합니다.
I'll talk a little bit more about it
함수의 세부
when I go into details of the functions.
사항에 대해 이야기할 때 좀 더 말씀드리겠습니다.
In all of the layers, we often use same activation functions.
모든 층에서 우리는 종종 동일한 활성화 함수를 사용합니다.
But as I said, sometimes, in the later layers, or the output
하지만 제가 말했듯이, 때때로
layer, we use a activation sigmoid function
후속 층이나 출력 층에서는 시그모이드
and/or tangent function, but commonly yes.
함수와/또는 탄젠트 함수를 사용하지만, 일반적으로 그렇습니다.
And the question was, if we use the same across the networks,
질문은, 네트워크 전반에 걸쳐 모든 뉴런에 대해 동일한
the entire network, same function for all of the neurons?
함수를 사용하는지였습니다.
OK, continuing to what we were talking
좋습니다, 우리가 이야기하고 있던
about, which is the implementation of these models,
신경망 모델의 구현으로 계속
these neural network.
진행하겠습니다.
So there is a very simple way.
매우 간단한 방법이 있습니다.
I mean, building a neural network,
파이썬에서 두 개의 층을
a two layer neural network, in Python
가진 신경망을
is just less than 20 lines of code.
구축하는 것은 20줄도 안 되는 코드입니다.
Very simple, define our network as I talked
매우 간단하게, 제가 이야기한 차원으로 네트워크를
about the dimensionalities.
정의합니다.
N is the number of samples.
N은 샘플의 수입니다.
D_in is the dimensionality of the input.
D_in은 입력의 차원입니다.
And D_out is the dimensionality of the output.
D_out은 출력의 차원입니다.
And h, the number of neurons in the hidden layer.
h는 은닉층의 뉴런 수입니다.
And we talked about-- this is just creating x and y
우리는 x와 y를 생성하고 W를
and randomly initializing W's.
무작위로 초기화하는 것에 대해 이야기했습니다.
Then we have the forward pass, which
그 다음에는 순전파가 있습니다.
means applying W's to the inputs, layer by layer,
이는 입력에 W를 적용하고, 층별로
and ultimately creating the output, the predicted wise,
진행하여 최종적으로 출력, 예측 값을 생성하고, 마지막으로 손실
and finally calculating the loss function
함수를 계산하고 그 손실 값을
and outputting that loss value.
출력하는 것을 의미합니다.
After the forward pass, we need an optimization process, a way
순전파 후에는 최적화 과정이 필요합니다. 이는 분석적
to calculate the analytical gradients
기울기를 계산하고 생성된 기울기를
and use those gradients that are created
사용하여 W1과 W2를 최적화하기 위해
to run gradient descent to optimize W1 and W2,
경량 하강법을 실행하는 방법입니다. 기본적으로
basically taking one step towards the optimal value
네트워크의 최적 값으로 한
of the network.
걸음 나아가는 것입니다.
But this part, calculating the analytical gradient,
하지만 이 부분, 즉 분석적 기울기를
is the most important part in here
계산하는 것은 우리가 많이 다루지 않은
that we haven't very much gone into.
가장 중요한 부분입니다.
So this is the--
그래서 이 강의의
almost the rest of this lecture is
거의 나머지 부분은
about making this work and scale in different settings.
이를 작동시키고 다양한 설정에서 확장하는 것에 관한 것입니다.
So after training and building such a neural network,
이러한 신경망을 훈련하고 구축한 후, 은닉층에서
depending on how many nodes we use in the hidden layer,
사용하는 노드 수에 따라 두
you see that we can identify, we can
클래스 간의
get different patterns of separation between the two
분리 패턴을 식별할 수
classes.
있습니다.
And more neurons often means more capacity
더 많은 뉴런은 종종 더
to learn more complex functions and better separation
복잡한 함수를 학습하고 노드, 포인트의 더
of the nodes, the points.
나은 분리를 위한 더 많은 용량을 의미합니다.
If you take a look at this, this is very much similar to this.
이것을 보면, 이것은 매우 유사합니다.
This pattern I'm showing here is similar to the one
여기 보여주는 패턴은 두 번째
that I showed in the second lecture, where we are talking
강의에서 k 최근접 이웃에 대해 이야기할 때
about k nearest neighbor.
보여준 것과 유사합니다.
And when we had only k equal to 1, the one nearest neighbor
k가 1일 때, 즉 최근접 이웃 프레임워크를 사용할 때, 이는 더
framework, it was very much similar to using more neurons.
많은 뉴런을 사용하는 것과 매우 유사했습니다.
So same type of arguments happen here
따라서 네트워크에
that if we give a lot of capacity to the network, then
많은 용량을 부여하면 과적합 문제가
we will have some overfitting problems.
발생할 수 있습니다.
We won't be able to generalize to unseen data.
보지 못한 데이터에 일반화할 수 없게 됩니다.
But there are many different solutions for this as well.
하지만 이와 관련된 다양한 해결책이 있습니다.
And one thing that-- as a rule of thumb,
그리고 제가 강조하고 싶은 한
what I want to highlight here for you
가지는 신경망의
is to not use the size of the neural network as a regularizer.
크기를 정규화기로 사용하지 않는 것입니다.
We don't often use that as a hyperparameter
우리는 이 네트워크 크기를 미세 조정하기 위한
to finetune this network size.
하이퍼파라미터로 자주 사용하지 않습니다.
Although, we experiment with different values of the network
다만, 우리는 네트워크 크기와 관련된
size and related hyperparameters.
하이퍼파라미터의 다양한 값으로 실험합니다.
But what we often do is we go with a little bit of a bigger
하지만 우리가 자주 하는 것은 필요한 것보다 약간 더 큰 네트워크를
network that we need.
사용하는 것입니다.
And then we use the regularization
그런 다음 정규화와
and this regularizer, and specifically,
이 정규화기, 특히
this regularization hyperparameter
이 정규화 하이퍼파라미터를 사용하여 다양한 설정을
to check the different setups.
확인합니다.
So what we often tune is the regularization
그래서 우리가 자주 조정하는 것은 정규화와
and regularization hyperparameter and not
정규화 하이퍼파라미터이지,
necessarily the network size itself.
반드시 네트워크 크기 자체는 아닙니다.
OK, this is the concept of neural networks in a nutshell.
좋습니다, 이것이 신경망의 개념을 간단히 설명한 것입니다.
But we have heard about neural networks
하지만 우리는 신경망과 그것이 생물학적
and how they could be related to the biological--
영감을 받을 수 있는 방법에
there are some biological inspirations.
대해 들어왔습니다.
So I'll talk a little bit about it, but there is a question.
그래서 이에 대해 조금 이야기하겠지만 질문이 있습니다.
Basically, your question is, why is the model more underfitting
기본적으로 당신의 질문은, 여기서 람다 값을 증가시킬 때 모델이
when we increase the value of lambda here?
왜 더 과소적합되는가입니다.
Yes, so just to quickly answer that question,
네, 그 질문에 빠르게 답하자면, 람다 값은
the value of lambda is controlling
정규화기가 전체
how much contribution the regularizer
손실에 얼마나 기여해야
should have in the overall loss.
하는지를 조절합니다.
And the larger contribution that you have on the regularizer--
정규화기에 대한 기여가 클수록-- 그리고 그 정규화기는 W에
and remember that regularizer was defined on W's.
대해 정의되었다는 것을 기억하세요.
So it's constraining the W's.
그래서 W를 제약하고 있습니다.
It's giving you less freedom to the values on W's.
W의 값에 대한 자유를 줄이고 있습니다.
So less freedom equals a little bit more generic boundaries,
자유가 적다는 것은 조금 더 일반적인 경계를 의미하며, 반드시 세부적인
not necessarily giving you those detailed values,
값이나 경계의 세부적인 부분을
or detailed parts of the boundaries.
제공하지는 않습니다.
So if you constrain the model too much, even with regularizer,
그래서 모델을 너무 많이 제약하면,
you're also going to get values like that,
정규화기가 있더라도 그런 값이나 결정 경계를
decision boundaries like that.
얻게 됩니다.
Yes, the right regularizer always overfits--
네, 올바른 정규화기는 항상
it prevents overfitting.
과적합을 방지합니다.
Again, you are creating a compromise,
다시 말해, 당신은 손실과
a balance between the loss, like predicting the right output.
올바른 출력을 예측하는 것 사이의 균형을 만들어야 합니다.
So the first part of the loss is predicting the right output.
손실의 첫 번째 부분은 올바른 출력을 예측하는 것입니다.
The second part is only playing with the values of the weights,
두 번째 부분은 가중치의 값만 다루고, 더
doesn't care about the outputs anymore.
이상 출력에 신경 쓰지 않습니다.
If you overweight this, you're not
이것을 과도하게 가중치를 두면,
going to get very good classifiers.
좋은 분류기를 얻지 못할 것입니다.
So creating a balance, regularizer is always good.
그래서 균형을 만드는 것이 좋습니다. 정규화기는 항상 좋습니다.
But nothing is good if you use too much of it.
하지만 너무 많이 사용하면 아무것도 좋지 않습니다.
Can you go over again why we would
왜 정규화를 선택해야
want to choose the regularization rather
하는지 다시 설명해
than the size [INAUDIBLE]?
주실 수 있나요?
So there are many different reasons.
여러 가지 이유가 있습니다.
One of them is size of the network.
그 중 하나는 네트워크의 크기입니다.
You're building the networks.
당신은 네트워크를 구축하고 있습니다.
You're going to build networks that,
때때로 결과를
sometimes, that you have to run them for few days
얻기 위해 며칠 동안 실행해야 하는 네트워크를
to get some results.
구축해야 합니다.
So networks, what we often do is,
그래서 우리가 자주 하는 것은 네트워크의
we start increasing the number of parameters
매개변수 수를 증가시키는 것입니다,
in networks, until we see some levels of overfitting.
과적합의 수준이 보일 때까지.
So that's the time that we know that the network is actually
그때 우리는 네트워크가 실제로 데이터의 패턴을
understanding the patterns in the data
이해하고 있으며 이제
and is now able to memorize the data.
데이터를 기억할 수 있다는 것을 알게 됩니다.
And that's the time that we try to minimize the overfitting
그때 우리는 네트워크를 정규화하여
by regularizing the network.
과적합을 최소화하려고 합니다.
So regularization plays an important factor there.
따라서 정규화는 중요한 요소로 작용합니다.
So if we go too high on the number of parameters, number
매개변수의 수나 네트워크의 복잡성이 너무
of complexity of the network, then that's
높아지면 문제가 발생할
going to be causing a problem.
것입니다.
We never often do that.
우리는 그렇게 하는 경우가 거의 없습니다.
We often, for a new problem, start with smaller networks
우리는 종종 새로운 문제에 대해 작은
and increase that after with--
네트워크로 시작하고, 이후 정규화를
correct that with the regularizer.
통해 이를 수정합니다.
For a given problem, how do we know
주어진 문제에 대해 해결하는 데
how many neurons we need to solve the problem?
필요한 뉴런의 수는 어떻게 알 수 있을까요?
That's based on empirical research work
이는 경험적 연구 작업과 유사한 유형의 다른 사례를
and looking at other similar type of-- there
기반으로 하며, 모든 경우에 적용되는
is no one prescription for all.
정답은 없습니다.
You have to look at other counterparts,
유사한 데이터로 훈련된 다른 네트워크를
other types of networks that were trained on similar data,
살펴보고 그 범위에서
start from that range.
시작해야 합니다.
And then often, you do a number of experiments
그리고 종종, 네트워크의 복잡성을
yourself to balance and increase or decrease
조정하기 위해 여러 실험을
the complexity of the network.
수행합니다.
So it's often and always pretty much bound to exploration.
그래서 이는 탐색에 매우 의존합니다.
So your question is, are there any theoretical and foundational
따라서 귀하의 질문은 어떤 이론적이고 기초적인 작업이
work done to see which ones to use,
수행되어 어떤 활성화 함수를 사용하고, 몇 개의 레이어를
which activation functions to use, and how many layers to use?
사용할지 결정하는지에 대한 것입니다.
There are so many research and papers
이와 관련된 많은 연구와
out analyzing these and also some methods
논문이 있으며, 이러한
for optimizing all of these meta or hyperparameters
메타 또는 하이퍼파라미터를 최적화하는 방법도
of the networks.
있습니다.
We are not going to get into them in detail
우리는 이들에 대해 자세히 다루지
because, again, a big part of it is
않을 것입니다. 다시 말해, 그
based on-- very much dependent on the data set, the problem
대부분은 데이터 세트와 해결하려는 문제에
you're solving.
매우 의존합니다.
And so the best answer to your question
따라서 귀하의 질문에 대한 최선의 답변은, 예, 그런
is, yes, there are some works out there.
작업이 존재한다는 것입니다.
But again, each of those make assumptions
하지만 다시 말해, 각 작업은 귀하의 응용
that may not be necessarily true for your application,
프로그램이나 문제에 반드시 맞지 않을 수 있는
or problem.
가정을 합니다.
So what happens is, there are some biological inspirations.
그래서 발생하는 것은 몇 가지 생물학적 영감이 있습니다.
Again, these inspirations are very much very loose.
다시 말해, 이러한 영감은 매우 느슨합니다.
If there is a neuroscientist sitting here,
여기 앉아 있거나
or is watching online, do not take all of the examples
온라인으로 보고 있는 신경과학자가 있다면, 제가
that I'm giving you, or talking about as the ground truth.
드리는 모든 예시를 절대적인 진리로 받아들이지 마세요.
But generally, what happens in neurons--
하지만 일반적으로 뉴런에서
and this is a visualization of a neuron--
발생하는 일은 이렇습니다. 이것은 뉴런의
it does have a cell body that often aggregates
시각화입니다. 뉴런은 종종 수상돌기를
the impulses carried through dendrites to the cell body
통해 전달된 자극을 집합하는 세포체를 가지고
itself, cell body.
있습니다.
And then using axons, those impulses
그리고 축삭을 사용하여, 그
are carried away to other neurons.
자극은 다른 뉴런으로 전달됩니다.
This is very much similar to what we are
이는 우리가 신경망에서 하는
doing in our neural networks.
것과 매우 유사합니다.
We often have a function that captures
우리는 종종 신호를 포착하는
the signals, all of the previous impulses,
함수를 가지고 있으며, 이전 레이어의 모든 자극과
activations from the previous layers.
활성화를 포함합니다.
And in the cell body, that function
그리고 세포체에서 그 함수는
is operated on the inputs and outputs the activations
입력에 대해 작동하여 활성화를 출력하고 다음 레이어,
and passes them to the next layer, next neuron.
다음 뉴런으로 전달합니다.
And that's, basically, why we need some sort of activation
기본적으로, 우리는 여기서
function here to create the impulses to increase,
값을 증가시키거나 감소시키기 위해 어떤
or decrease the values.
형태의 활성화 함수가 필요합니다.
So with that, again, there are many differences
따라서 다시 말해, 생물학적 뉴런과 우리가 구축하는
between biological neurons and how they could actually
신경망 간에는 많은 차이가
be very more complex than what neural networks
있으며, 생물학적 뉴런은 실제로 훨씬 더
we build look like.
복잡할 수 있습니다.
But generally, there are common concepts.
하지만 일반적으로 공통 개념이 있습니다.
Often, the neural networks that we build
우리가 구축하는 신경망은
are organized into regular patterns.
종종 규칙적인 패턴으로 구성됩니다.
And those patterns are because we
그러한 패턴은 신경망을
want to have better computational efficiency when we
구현할 때 더 나은 계산
implement the neural networks.
효율성을 원하기 때문입니다.
Although there has been research creating
복잡한 신경망을
these complex neural networks and trying to optimize,
만들고 최적화하려는 연구가
but again, in terms of results, they
있었지만, 결과 측면에서
are almost comparable with the regular functions,
우리는 종종 구축하는 일반적인 함수,
regular neural networks that we often build
일반적인 신경망과
and we'll be talking about in this class.
거의 비슷합니다.
I can't warn you enough on being careful with your brain
귀하의 두뇌 비유와 그것이 어떻게 해석될 수
analogies and how this could be interpreted.
있는지에 대해 조심하라고 경고할 수 없습니다.
So there are so many differences.
그래서 많은 차이가 있습니다.
And I'll just stop here and would
여기서 멈추고 신경과학 측면에 관심이
be happy to discuss if anybody was
있는 분들과
interested in the neuroscience aspect of things as well.
논의할 수 있으면 좋겠습니다.
So plugging everything in, we did have a scoring function.
모든 것을 연결하면, 우리는 점수 함수를 가지고 있었습니다.
This scoring function turns the inputs
이 점수 함수는 입력을 W의
through some W's weight vectors, or weight matrices into scores.
가중치 벡터 또는 가중치 행렬을 통해 점수로 변환합니다.
And what we often use as the loss function for the network
네트워크의 손실 함수로 자주 사용하는 것은 이러한 점수를 힌지 손실,
is using those scores either through hinge loss, or softmax,
소프트맥스 또는 다른 변형을
or other variations.
통해 사용하는 것입니다.
And in addition to that, we defined regularizers,
또한, 우리는 정규화기를 정의했으며, 이는
which ultimately give us the total loss of the data
궁극적으로 데이터 손실과 정규화기를
loss plus regularizer.
합한 총 손실을 제공합니다.
And we talked about this fact that in order
W1과 W2를
to be able to optimize W1 and W2,
최적화하기 위해 필요한
what we need is to be able to take
것은 L에 대한
the derivative of, the partial derivative of L with respect
W1과 W2의
to W1 and W2, partial L by W1 and W2.
부분 미분을 취할 수 있는 것입니다.
There are so many different details
우리가 인식해야 할
that we have to be aware of.
다양한 세부 사항이 많습니다.
First, building these functions and then taking the derivatives
먼저 이러한 함수를 만들고 미분을 취하고 이를
and writing them down is often tedious.
기록하는 것은 종종 번거롭습니다.
There are lots of matrix calculations
행렬 계산이 많고
and need a lot of work on the paper
실제로 신경망을 구현하기 전에
before you can actually implement a neural network.
많은 작업이 필요합니다.
The other challenge, the other problem
다른 문제는
is, what if you want to change the loss slightly
논문에서 했던 것과 약간 다른 손실로
different from what we have done in the paper, all
변경하고 싶을 경우 모든 계산을 다시
of the calculations over?
해야 한다는 것입니다.
So in that case, again, we have to redo the entire thing.
그 경우, 다시 전체 작업을 수행해야 합니다.
And finally, this becomes intractable and, sometimes,
결국 손실 함수가 복잡하면 이는 다루기 힘들고
infeasible if the loss function is complex.
때로는 불가능해집니다.
So with complex functions, that's going to be even harder.
복잡한 함수와 함께라면 더욱 어려워질 것입니다.
But there is a better idea, something that is often
하지만 더 나은 아이디어가 있습니다.
used in our implementations.
이는 우리의 구현에서 자주 사용됩니다.
And I'm going to go into a few examples
오늘 몇 가지 예를 들어 모든
today just to make sure everybody is on the same page
사람이 같은 페이지에 있고 이
and understands these topics.
주제를 이해하도록 하겠습니다.
And that is computational graphs and the idea of backpropagation.
그것은 계산 그래프와 역전파의 개념입니다.
Computational graphs are putting together
계산 그래프는 신경망의 모든 연산을
all of the operations in the neural network
모아 단계별로
and creating that step-by-step thing
구성하고 입력과 기본적으로 필요한 모든
and start from the inputs and all of the parameters
매개변수에서 시작하여 최종
that are basically needed and get the loss
출력, 즉 최종 레이어로
as the final output, final layer.
손실을 얻는 것입니다.
So in this case, we had a loss function,
이 경우 손실 함수는 소프트맥스
which could be a softmax function,
함수 또는 힌지 손실
or a hinge loss function.
함수일 수 있습니다.
Whatever it is, it's the loss function,
무엇이든 간에,
which is added to the regularizer, the function RW.
이는 정규화기 RW에 추가되는 손실 함수입니다.
And R has W as its input.
R은 W를 입력으로 가집니다.
So these two added together calculate, or create the loss.
따라서 이 두 개를 더하여 손실을 계산하거나 생성합니다.
And before doing the, or having the loss calculated,
손실을 계산하기 전에, 우리는 종종
we often also need to aggregate x and W and create the score.
x와 W를 집계하고 점수를 생성해야 합니다.
This is a multiplication function.
이것은 곱셈 함수입니다.
This is actually very useful because most
이는 실제로 매우 유용합니다. 왜냐하면 우리가
of the neural networks that we build are also
구축하는 대부분의 신경망은 그래픽 카드
they have graphical card representations.
표현을 가지고 있기 때문입니다.
And all of these complex functions
모든 이러한 복잡한 함수는
could be shown with the same framework.
동일한 프레임워크로 표시될 수 있습니다.
And then we can use this and build their computation graph,
그런 다음 이를 사용하여 입력 이미지 또는 입력 데이터에서 시작하여
starting from input image or input data.
계산 그래프를 구축할 수 있습니다.
There are a bunch of weights throughout the network.
네트워크 전반에 걸쳐 많은 가중치가 있습니다.
And finally, there is the loss function.
마지막으로 손실 함수가 있습니다.
And again, this is useful because there
다시 말해, 이는 복잡한 신경망,
are some complex neural networks, like this neural
예를 들어 이 신경 튜링 기계에
Turing machine.
유용합니다.
And that is actually used for temporal and sequential data.
이는 시간적 및 순차적 데이터에 사용됩니다.
So there is a lot of unrolling of this machine.
따라서 이 기계의 많은 언롤링이 있습니다.
And if we have to do all of the work manually by hand,
모든 작업을 수동으로
this is going to be intractable and not feasible.
수행해야 한다면 이는 다루기 힘들고 불가능할 것입니다.
And that's why when we build this computational graph,
그래서 우리가 이 계산 그래프를 구축할
the solution to that is backpropagation.
때, 그 해결책이 역전파입니다.
And I want to start with a very simple example.
그리고 저는 매우 간단한 예로 시작하고 싶습니다.
So we start with a function f of x, y, and z,
그래서 우리는 x, y, z의 함수 f로 시작합니다.
which is x plus y multiplied by z.
이는 x 더하기 y 곱하기 z입니다.
And if I draw the computational graph for this function,
이 함수의 계산 그래프를 그리면,
you see we have an operation, which is the addition
x와 y 사이의 덧셈 연산이
operation between x and y.
있습니다.
And then we have a multiplication
그리고 그 덧셈
between that addition of x and y multiplied by z.
x와 y에 z를 곱하는 곱셈이 있습니다.
So given an input setup of x equal to minus 2, y equal to 5,
입력 값이 x는 -2, y는 5, z는
and z equal to minus 4, now actually,
-4일 때, 이제
we can make all of the calculations
실제로 모든
for and do this, the forward pass,
계산을 하고 신경망에서 순전파를
stepping forward in the neural network.
진행할 수 있습니다.
The first step is adding x and y, which gives us 3.
첫 번째 단계는 x와 y를 더하는 것으로, 결과는 3입니다.
And in order to be able to understand the steps
단계별로 이해할 수 있도록
and step-by-step, I'm giving a name to it.
이름을 붙이겠습니다.
So q equals x plus y.
그래서 q는 x 더하기 y입니다.
And if I want to calculate the partial derivatives of q
q에 대한 x와 y의 부분 미분을
with respect to both x and y, it's
계산하려면 매우
very simple because we have the formulation here between q
간단합니다. q와 x, y 사이의 공식이 있기
and x and y.
때문입니다.
The formulation is there.
공식이 있습니다.
The derivatives, the partial q by x equals 1 and partial q by y
q에 대한 x의 부분 미분은 1이고, y에 대한
equals 1 as well.
부분 미분도 1입니다.
So this is a simple setup.
그래서 이것은 간단한 설정입니다.
We know it exists.
우리는 그것이 존재한다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So just keep it in the back of our minds.
그러니 마음속에 두세요.
Then the second operation is f equals q multiplied by z.
그 다음 연산은 f는 q 곱하기 z입니다.
Again, since we have this function,
다시 말해, 이 함수가
it's very easy to write the partial derivatives.
있으므로 부분 미분을 쓰는 것이 매우 쉽습니다.
Partial f by q equals z.
f에 대한 q의 부분 미분은 z입니다.
And f by z equals q.
그리고 f에 대한 z의 부분 미분은 q입니다.
So it's swap between z and q.
그래서 z와 q가 서로 바뀝니다.
I'm hoping that everybody knows all
모두가 선형 대수학에
of these from linear algebra.
대해 알고 있기를 바랍니다.
So if you don't, you should definitely
모르신다면 꼭 확인하고
check it out and remind yourself because these are actually
상기시켜야 합니다. 왜냐하면
very, very important algebra in general
이것들은 이번 분기 나머지에 매우 중요한
for the rest of the quarter.
대수이기 때문입니다.
What we want and what we need in this setup,
우리가 이 설정에서 원하는
and to complete this example of backpropagation,
것과 필요한 것은
we need the partial derivative of f with respect
f에 대한 x, y,
to x, y, and z.
z의 부분 미분입니다.
How we start and how our backpropagation implements
우리가 시작하는 방법과 역전파가 이를
this is to start at the front of the net--
구현하는 방법은 네트워크의 앞쪽, 즉
at the end of the network.
끝에서 시작하는 것입니다.
And we start going back, backpropagating
그리고 우리는 뒤로 가서 모든 그래디언트를
all of the gradients.
역전파합니다.
And this is basically a recursive process
이것은 기본적으로 실행될 재귀
that will be running.
프로세스입니다.
So derivative of f with respect to f is what?
f에 대한 f의 미분은 무엇인가요?
It's the thing with respect to itself.
그것은 자기 자신에 대한 것입니다.
So it's always the last part, the derivative
그래서 항상 마지막 부분, 손실
of loss function with respect to itself is always 1.
함수에 대한 미분은 항상 1입니다.
If I want to backprop, the most immediate one is z.
역전파를 원한다면 가장 즉각적인 것은 z입니다.
You can see here that we have z.
여기서 z가 있습니다.
And for this one, if I calculate the derivative of f with respect
이 경우 f에 대한 z의 미분을 계산하면
to z, we already have it.
이미 가지고 있습니다.
F with respect to z is equal to q.
f에 대한 z는 q와 같습니다.
So whatever the value of q is goes to this as the gradient
따라서 q의 값이 무엇이든 이 그래디언트로
as well.
전달됩니다.
Next, we have q.
다음은 q입니다.
Q is the next one-- our next one that is directly connected to f.
Q는 다음 것, 즉 f와 직접 연결된 다음 것입니다.
So this is also easy to compute because we have derivative
따라서 이는 q에 대한 f의 도함수를 가지고 있기 때문에
of f with respect to q.
계산하기 쉽습니다.
We have also already calculated that it's equal to z.
우리는 이미 그것이 z와 같다는 것을 계산했습니다.
Whatever z is, that's the value of derivative here minus 4.
z가 무엇이든, 여기서의 도함수 값은 -4입니다.
Next, we have y, which is directly before q.
다음은 q 바로 앞에 있는 y입니다.
And we know that y and f, although we need derivative
y와 f는 연결되어 있지 않지만,
of f with respect to y, but y and f
y에 대한 f의 도함수가
are not directly connected.
필요합니다.
And that's where we use the chain rule, where
그래서 우리는 체인 규칙을
we split the calculation of derivatives with respect
사용하여 중간 변수에 대한 도함수 계산을
to the variable in the middle.
나눕니다.
So partial f by y equals to partial f by q, q by y.
따라서 y에 대한 부분 f는 q에 대한 부분 f와 q에 대한 y의 곱입니다.
So this is how the chain rule could be written in this case.
이것이 이 경우 체인 규칙을 작성하는 방법입니다.
And now, I want to introduce you to two important new terms--
이제 두 가지 중요한 새로운 용어를 소개하고 싶습니다: 로컬
local gradient and upstream gradient.
그래디언트와 업스트림 그래디언트입니다.
Upstream gradient is often the gradient
업스트림
that comes from the end of the network to this current node
그래디언트는 종종 네트워크의 끝에서 현재 노드로 오는 그래디언트입니다.
And then the local gradient is the gradient
그리고 로컬 그래디언트는
of the nodes, what the input of the node
노드의 입력과
is, with a gradient of its output with respect
출력에 대한 그래디언트입니다.
So it's the local gradient.
그래서 이것이 로컬 그래디언트입니다.
So defining these is actually not too hard because f by q,
이들을 정의하는 것은 실제로 어렵지 않습니다. 왜냐하면 q에 대한 f의 값이
you already have the value.
이미 있기 때문입니다.
Q by y, we also already have the value.
y에 대한 q의 값도 이미 있습니다.
So it's 1 multiplied by z, and the value will become minus 4.
그래서 1에 z를 곱하면 값은 -4가 됩니다.
Same story, and it's for the other variable, x.
같은 이야기이고, 다른 변수 x에 대해서도 마찬가지입니다.
Here, the local gradient upstream
여기서 로컬 그래디언트 업스트림은 다시
could, again, be written down with this chain rule.
이 체인 규칙으로 작성될 수 있습니다.
And it also results in minus 4 and gives us--
그리고 이것은 -4로 결과가 나오며, 두 경우
because in both cases, the gradient with respect to x or y
모두 x 또는 y에 대한 그래디언트는 이미
was already 1.
1이었습니다.
So both of them get the same value.
그래서 두 값이 동일합니다.
So with this computational setup and the computational graph,
이 계산 설정과 계산 그래프 덕분에 우리가
it becomes very easy to modularize what we want to do.
하고자 하는 일을 모듈화하기 매우 쉬워집니다.
For every single node in the neural network,
신경망의 모든 노드에 대해 x와 y를
having x and y as input, or whatever else,
입력으로, 또는 다른 무엇이든,
and z as the output, what we need are, first,
z를 출력으로 가질 때, 우리가 필요한 것은 먼저 로컬
the local gradients.
그래디언트입니다.
Which we can always-- we have the function f.
우리는 항상 함수 f를 가지고 있습니다.
It's a function of x and y.
x와 y의 함수입니다.
So the gradient of output with respect to each of the inputs,
따라서 각 입력에 대한 출력의 그래디언트를 계산하는 것은
it's easy to calculate for every single node.
모든 노드에 대해 쉽습니다.
And what we need to be able to backpropagate
그리고 우리가 역전파를 위해 필요한 것은
is the upstream gradient.
업스트림 그래디언트입니다.
And the backpropagation process is giving us
역전파 과정은 이 업스트림 그래디언트를
the power to get this upstream gradient as step-by-step.
단계별로 얻을 수 있는 힘을 제공합니다.
So when we are at this node, we also
따라서 이 노드에 있을 때,
have the upstream gradient already
우리는 이미 미래 노드에서
calculated from the future nodes.
계산된 업스트림 그래디언트를 가지고 있습니다.
And that's what we need.
그리고 그것이 우리가 필요한 것입니다.
What we can do after this is just
이후에 할 수 있는 것은 업스트림
to multiply the upstream gradient with the local gradient
그래디언트와 로컬 그래디언트를 곱하여 이제 우리가
and create what now we call downstream gradients.
다운스트림 그래디언트라고 부르는 것을 만드는 것입니다.
So the downstream gradients are going
따라서 다운스트림 그래디언트는
to be upstream gradients for the previous layers.
이전 레이어에 대한 업스트림 그래디언트가 될 것입니다.
So that's how we calculate that for x,
그래서 x에 대해 그렇게 계산하고,
same story when it comes to y.
y에 대해서도 같은 이야기입니다.
So this whole process gives us the power
그래서 이 전체 과정은 우리가 모든 것을 완전히
to create and calculate all of these completely
로컬에서 생성하고 계산할 수 있는 힘을
locally and a step-by-step go backwards
주며, 단계별로 거꾸로 가서 이전
and give it to the previous nodes
노드에 전달하여 그들이
so they can continue their process.
계속할 수 있도록 합니다.
So again, this is one of the most fundamental operations
그래서 다시 말하지만, 이것은 모든 신경망과
in all of neural networks and many optimization
여러 정보 층을 포함하는 많은 최적화
processes involving multiple layers of information.
과정에서 가장 기본적인 작업 중 하나입니다.
If I understand the question correctly, you're saying,
질문을 제대로 이해했다면, 우리는 직관적으로 기울기가 무엇을
how can we understand this, intuitively,
하고 있는지 이해할 수 있는
what the gradients are doing?
방법을 묻고 있는 것입니다.
So let's take one step back and see
그래서 한 걸음 물러서서 우리가 왜 여기
why we are here to begin with.
있는지 살펴보겠습니다.
What we needed was to identify to calculate
우리가 필요했던 것은 W1과
the gradients of the loss function
W2, 일반적으로 W에
with respect to W1 and W2 and W's in general,
대한 손실 함수의 기울기를 계산하는
to be able to take a step in the negative direction
것이었고, 기울기의 반대 방향으로 최적의 값, 최적의
of, in the opposite direction of the gradients
손실을 찾기 위해 한
to be able to find the optimal value, optimal loss.
걸음 나아갈 수 있어야 했습니다.
So in order to do that, we need gradient of L loss
그래서 이를 위해 우리는 모든 것에 대한 L 손실의
with respect to everything.
기울기가 필요합니다.
So what we are doing is, we are just moving gradient of L
우리가 하는 것은 네트워크의 모든 변수에 대한 L의
with respect to all variables in the network,
기울기를 네트워크의 모든 값으로
back to every single value of the network,
이동시키는 것이며, 전체 네트워크에
without sitting down and writing the function
대한 함수를 앉아서 작성하지 않고도
for the entire network.
가능합니다.
If the network has 100 layers, we're
네트워크에 100개의 층이 있다면, 우리는 100개의
not going to be sitting down and writing the function for all
층 각각에 대한 함수를 앉아서
of the 100 layers separately.
작성하지 않을 것입니다.
This is how we backpropagate step-by-step
이것이 우리가 단계별로
to get the values that we need for that optimization
역전파하여 네트워크에 통합될 모든
process of every single weight that is going to be incorporated
가중치의 최적화 과정에 필요한
in the network.
값을 얻는 방법입니다.
OK, another example, so this is a little bit
좋아요, 또 다른 예시입니다. 이것은 가중치와 x의
more complex function, a function of weights and x.
조금 더 복잡한 함수입니다.
And we have 1 over 1 plus e to the power of linear combination
그리고 우리는 1을 1 더하기 e의 x와 w의
of x and w.
선형 조합의 거듭제곱으로 나누었습니다.
So there are a bunch of multiplications, additions,
그래서 곱셈, 덧셈, 부정, exp 함수가
negation, and the exp function, and ultimately,
있으며, 궁극적으로 우리가 계산한
the 1 over whatever we calculated function.
함수의 1로 나누어집니다.
So with all of those, let's look at this example that we have,
이 모든 것을 가지고, W0, x0, W1, x1, W2에
specific values for W0, x0, W1, x1, and W2.
대한 특정 값을 가진 이 예제를 살펴보겠습니다.
With these given values, we can do the forward pass,
이 주어진 값으로 우리는 순방향 패스를 수행하고
calculate every single value that we have in this process.
이 과정에서 우리가 가진 모든 값을 계산할 수 있습니다.
And just to remind you, we do have some
그리고 여러분에게 상기시키기 위해,
of the details, some of the--
우리는 exp 함수에
we know for an exp function, e to the power of x,
대한 몇 가지 세부 사항이 있으며, e의 x에 대한
what its derivative is with respect to x
도함수가 x에 대한 상수 곱셈이
constant multiplication.
무엇인지 알고 있습니다.
Always, the derivative is the constant value itself,
항상 도함수는 상수
1 over x, as a derivative of minus 1 over x2.
값 자체인 1/x의 도함수는 -1/x²입니다.
These are, again, what we know from algebra.
이것들은 다시 말하지만, 우리가 대수에서 아는 것입니다.
And if it's a constant addition, it's always,
그리고 상수 덧셈일 경우, 항상
the derivative is equal to 1.
도함수는 1과 같습니다.
So as I said, always in the very beginning
그래서 제가 말했듯이, 네트워크의
at the end of the network, the derivative
시작과 끝에서 L에 대한
of L with respect to L is always equal to 1.
도함수는 항상 1과 같습니다.
So that's where we start using this rule,
그래서 여기서 우리는 1/x 함수의 도함수를
the derivative of function 1/x.
사용하는 것입니다.
Now, we can calculate-- upstream,
이제 우리는 계산할 수 있습니다.
I said, it's 1 always at the end.
상류에서는 항상 1입니다.
The local gradient could be minus 1 over x2.
로컬 기울기는 -1/x²일 수 있습니다.
What is the value of x?
x의 값은 무엇입니까?
Whatever the input is.
입력이 무엇이든 상관없습니다.
So this calculation results in minus 0.53.
그래서 이 계산의 결과는 -0.53입니다.
So minus 0.53 is the downstream gradient,
-0.53은 다음 것에 대한 상류 기울기를
which defines the upstream gradient for the next one.
정의하는 하류 기울기입니다.
And in the next, again, the function
그리고 다음 단계에서, 여기의
here is just the constant addition,
함수는 상수 덧셈이며, 우리는
where we know that the local gradient equals to 1.
로컬 기울기가 1과 같다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
So 1 multiplied by upstream gradient, same value, goes back.
그래서 1에 상류 기울기를 곱하면 같은 값이 다시 돌아갑니다.
And next step is the exp function.
다음 단계는 exp 함수입니다.
So for that, again, the upstream,
그래서 그에 대해, 다시 상류에서 우리는 이미 값을
we already have the value.
가지고 있습니다.
For the local gradient, it's e to the power of x.
로컬 기울기는 e의 x의 거듭제곱입니다.
What is x?
x는 무엇인가요?
The input of this step minus 1.
이 단계의 입력에서 1을 뺀 값입니다.
So calculating this will give us minus 0.2.
그래서 이를 계산하면 -0.2가 됩니다.
And this goes back to the next step.
그리고 이것은 다음 단계로 돌아갑니다.
Here, we, again, have a multiplication
여기서 우리는 다시 상수와의
with a constant number, which defines the local gradient
곱셈이 있으며, 이는 지역 기울기를
equal to that number, or that constant value,
그 숫자 또는 상수 값과 같게 정의하고
and defining the new gradient, downstream gradient.
새로운 기울기, 하류 기울기를 정의합니다.
And going back, now here, we have an addition function,
그리고 돌아가면,
where we are getting some data, some information-- sorry,
여기에는 두 개의 서로 다른 값의 입력을
two inputs of the different values here.
받는 덧셈 함수가 있습니다.
And again, if you want to calculate the upstream gradient,
다시 말해, 상류 기울기를 계산하고 싶다면 0.
it's 0.2.
2입니다.
Already, we have it.
이미 우리는 그것을 가지고 있습니다.
The downstream, the local gradients will be equal to 1
하류, 지역 기울기는 두 값 간의 덧셈이므로
because it's just an addition between two values.
1이 됩니다.
And an addition, the derivative of x
x와 y에 대한
plus y with respect to both x and y is always 1.
x+y의 도함수는 항상 1입니다.
So both inputs will be the same.
그래서 두 입력은 동일할 것입니다.
Then
그런
We have multiplication operations
다음 우리는 상류 기울기와
with multiplication upstream gradient.
곱셈 연산을 가지고 있습니다.
Again, we have the values.
다시 우리는 값을 가지고 있습니다.
And the local gradients with respect to a multiplication
곱셈에 대한 지역 기울기는 항상 예를
is, if we always have, say, for example,
들어 a와 x를 곱할
a multiplied by x, the derivative of this with respect
때, x에 대한 도함수는
to x is always the other variable.
항상 다른 변수입니다.
So here, for the first one, it's minus 1,
그래서 여기서 첫 번째는 -1, 즉 x의
which is the value of x.
값입니다.
And for the second one, it's 2, which is the value of w.
두 번째는 2, 즉 w의 값입니다.
So the other variable, whatever the value it has.
그래서 다른 변수는 어떤 값을 가지고 있든지 간에.
So with that, we can calculate everything and then
그래서 이를 통해 모든 것을 계산할 수 있고
also calculate the ones with respect to W1 and x1.
W1과 x1에 대한 것도 계산할 수 있습니다.
Again, we made all of these calculations,
다시 말해, 우리는 이러한
so we can identify how much W should
모든 계산을 했으므로 W가 네트워크의
be changed in order to step towards the optimal point
최적 지점으로 나아가기 위해 얼마나 변경되어야 하는지 식별할
in the network.
수 있습니다.
So this was another example.
그래서 이것은 또 다른 예였습니다.
There are so many different ways to draw a computational graph.
계산 그래프를 그리는 방법은 정말 많습니다.
This was not the only one that I explained.
이것이 제가 설명한 유일한 방법은 아닙니다.
So we can actually lump all of the functions
그래서 우리는 실제로 모든 함수를 함께
together and define a sigmoid because this is basically
묶고 시그모이드를 정의할 수 있습니다. 왜냐하면 이것은 기본적으로
a sigmoid of a linear function.
선형 함수의 시그모이드이기 때문입니다.
So the linear function could be here.
그래서 선형 함수는 여기 있을 수 있습니다.
And then all of these operations could be defined as sigmoid.
그리고 이러한 모든 연산은 시그모이드로 정의될 수 있습니다.
And actually, sigmoid is interesting and very useful
실제로 시그모이드는 흥미롭고 매우 유용하게
to use because the local gradient using sigmoid
사용할 수 있습니다. 왜냐하면 시그모이드를 사용할 때의 지역 기울기는 시그모이드
is dependent on sigmoid itself.
자체에 의존하기 때문입니다.
So the local gradient of sigmoid with respect to the variable x,
그래서 x에 대한 시그모이드의 지역 기울기는
if we do the calculations and simplify,
계산하고 단순화하면 1 -
it's 1 minus sigmoid multiplied by the sigmoid of the same x.
시그모이드 곱하기 같은 x의 시그모이드입니다.
So it's actually a very useful framework, useful function,
그래서 이는 실제로 매우 유용한 프레임워크, 유용한 함수이며
and easy.
쉽습니다.
And in order to calculate the downstream gradient, again,
그리고 하류 기울기를 계산하기 위해, 다시 말해 상류
what the upstream gradient was, was value 1.
기울기가 1이었습니다.
And if I calculate the local gradient, which
그리고 제가 지역 기울기를
is this function, replacing x with what the input was,
계산하면, 이 함수에서 x를
which is 1, it's how this will be calculated multiplied by 1
입력값인 1로 대체하면, 이는 1로 곱해져 0.
will be 0.2.
2가 됩니다.
Which is actually the exact same value
이는 실제로 이전에
that we had from before doing it separately.
별도로 계산했을 때와 정확히 같은 값입니다.
I want to summarize and say that there
저는 요약하고 싶습니다. 데이터에는 몇
are few patterns in the data, often very much in for the nodes
가지 패턴이 있으며, 종종 우리가 실제로 기억할 수 있는
that we can actually memorize.
노드에서 매우 많이 나타납니다.
There is add gate for the add gate.
더하기 게이트를 위한 더하기 게이트가 있습니다.
It's always a gradient distributor.
항상 기울기 분배기입니다.
Because of the properties of addition that I explained,
내가 설명한 덧셈의 특성 때문에,
the gradients will remain the same as whatever its input is.
기울기는 입력이 무엇이든 동일하게 유지됩니다.
For the multiplication gate, it's a swap function.
곱셈 게이트의 경우, 스왑 함수입니다.
Again, I told you, gradient of xy with respect to x
다시 말하지만, xy에 대한 x의 기울기는 y이고,
is y, with respect to y is x.
y에 대한 기울기는 x입니다.
So it's a swap.
그래서 스왑입니다.
And then there is copy gate.
그리고 복사 게이트가 있습니다.
And the copy gate, the operation that happens
복사 게이트에서 발생하는 작업은
is just an addition of what is coming to the network--
네트워크에 들어오는 것의 덧셈입니다--
to the node, or the gate.
노드 또는 게이트에.
And then ultimately, there is a max gate, which is actually
궁극적으로, 최대 게이트가 있으며, 이는 실제로
something that we use quite often, very much
우리가 자주 사용하는 것으로
similar to the ReLU function.
ReLU 함수와 매우 유사합니다.
That max gate has the gradient of--
그 최대 게이트는-- 입력 간의 최대값을
because it's taking a max between its inputs.
취하기 때문에 기울기를 가지고 있습니다.
So whichever the max value was, you just
그래서 최대값이 무엇이든,
route the gradients towards that direction.
기울기를 그 방향으로 라우팅합니다.
So with that, it's very simple to now implement
그로 인해 이제 신경망을 구현하는 것이 매우 간단해졌습니다.
a neural network, forward pass, compute all of the steps.
순전파를 수행하고 모든 단계를 계산합니다.
And then in the backward pass, we
그리고 역전파에서
start computing the gradients.
기울기를 계산하기 시작합니다.
In a step-by-step, I explained that the gradient
단계별로, 손실 함수의
of the loss function with respect to itself is always 1.
기울기가 항상 1이라는 것을 설명했습니다.
And then we start from the end of the network and go up.
그리고 네트워크의 끝에서 시작하여 위로 올라갑니다.
You can see here, that we are going up.
여기서 위로 올라가는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So this is the sigmoid function calculating the gradients,
그래서 이것은 기울기를 계산하는 시그모이드 함수입니다,
then going up.
그리고 위로 올라갑니다.
That was the add gate.
그것이 더하기 게이트였습니다.
We had another add gate.
또 다른 더하기 게이트가 있었습니다.
And then we had two multiply gates,
그리고 두 개의 곱셈 게이트가 있었으며,
which basically, very simply, gives us the implementations.
이는 기본적으로 매우 간단하게 구현을 제공합니다.
And with this type of formulation,
이러한 유형의 공식화로,
what we can do is just do some--
우리는 신경망의 모든 기능을
modularize every function in neural network
모듈화하고 필요한 모든 기능에 대한 순전파
and create the forward and backward
및 역전파
APIs for every single function that we
API를 생성할
need in the neural network.
수 있습니다.
So in this case, this is a multiplication gate that--
이 경우, 이것은 곱셈 게이트로--
because for multiplication, we need
곱셈을 위해서는
to access the inputs for use in the backward pass.
역전파에서 사용할 입력에 접근해야 합니다.
We often save them, memorize them, but then
우리는 종종 그것들을 저장하고 기억하지만,
calculate the forward pass values and then
그런 다음 순전파 값을
the backward pass, calculate the gradients.
계산하고 역전파에서 기울기를 계산합니다.
So this means we can write our functions and put the forward
그래서 이것은 우리가 우리의 함수를 작성하고 모든 순전파 및 역전파를
and backward passes all in.
포함할 수 있음을 의미합니다.
And this is how PyTorch operators right now look like.
현재 PyTorch 연산자는 이렇게 생겼습니다.
If you look at the sigmoid layer,
예를 들어, 시그모이드 레이어를
for example, it's just the forward pass.
보면, 그것은 단순히 순전파입니다.
Although in this very function it's not implemented.
비록 이 특정 함수에서는 구현되지 않았습니다.
It's somewhere else in the C++ code, in the C code,
C++ 코드의 다른 곳, C 코드에서 실제로
that it's actually implemented in PyTorch.
PyTorch에 구현되어 있습니다.
But then the backward pass of sigmoid
그러나 시그모이드의 역전파도
is also calculating the same function
우리가 방금 이야기한 동일한
that we just talked about.
함수를 계산하고 있습니다.
So far, what we've said--
지금까지 우리가 말한 것--
and I actually covered most of the examples
그리고 나는
that I wanted to cover in using the scalar values.
스칼라 값을 사용하는 대부분의 예제를 다루었습니다.
All of the examples were just scalar values.
모든 예제는 단지 스칼라 값이었습니다.
But we know that all of these operations
하지만 우리는 이러한 모든 연산이 실제로
could actually be implemented in vector or matrix forms,
벡터 또는 행렬 형태로 구현될 수 있다는
just expanding on that piece here.
것을 알고 있습니다, 여기서 그 부분을 확장합니다.
We talked about this, that with the scalar to scalar setting,
우리는 지금까지 스칼라에서 스칼라 설정에 대해
so far, what we've talked about for any input x and y
이야기했습니다. 입력 x와 y가 스칼라인
being scalars.
경우입니다.
So the derivative will also be a scalar.
따라서 도함수도 스칼라가 됩니다.
Which means if we change x by a small amount, how much
즉, x를 조금 변화시키면 y의 값이 얼마나
the value of y will change?
변하는지를 의미합니다.
If it's now vectorized and there are vectors,
이제 벡터화되었고,
if x is a vector of n elements and y
x가 n 요소의 벡터이고 y가
is a scalar, a vector to a scalar derivative,
스칼라인 경우, 벡터에서 스칼라로의
then in this case, the derivative
도함수는 이 경우에도 벡터가
will also be a vector.
됩니다.
And every single element in that vector
그리고 그 벡터의 각 요소는 x를
means if we change x by a small value, that value,
조금 변화시키면 y의 양이 얼마나 변하는지를
then how much the amount of y changes,
의미하며, y의 전체 양은 단일
then the entire amount of y because it's just
값이기 때문에
one single value.
그렇습니다.
And then there are also vector to vector frameworks,
또한 x와 y가 임의의 크기의
where x and y, both of them are vectors tours of arbitrary size.
벡터인 벡터에서 벡터로의 프레임워크도 있습니다.
And M, in those cases, the derivatives
이 경우 도함수는 행렬을
will form a matrix, or what we call Jacobians.
형성하며, 이를 야코비안이라고 부릅니다.
And for each of the elements in x,
x의 각 요소가 조금 변화하면 이
if it changes by a small amount, then
도함수는 y의 각
this derivative tells us how much each element of y
요소가 얼마나 변할지를
will be changed.
알려줍니다.
Again, look at the scripts here, they are not completely--
다시 말해, 여기 스크립트를 보면 완전히 같지
they're not the same.
않습니다.
They could be different.
서로 다를 수 있습니다.
For every single element in this Jacobian,
이 야코비안의 각 요소에는
there is a clear meaning.
명확한 의미가 있습니다.
And then how we can do, or see it and visualize it in here
그리고 벡터로 역전파를 수행하는 방법은
is that if you want to backprop with vectors--
x, y, z가 각각 dx,
say, x, y, and z are vectors of size dx, dy, dz.
dy, dz 크기의 벡터라고 가정할 때입니다.
Again, the loss derivative, L, is--
다시 말해, 손실 도함수 L은 항상 스칼라입니다. 왜냐하면
the loss itself is always a scalar
우리가 최소화하고자
because that's always one value we want to minimize.
하는 값은 항상 하나이기 때문입니다.
But then calculating the upstream gradient
그러나 상류 그래디언트를
will result in also a vector dz, same size as its variable z.
계산하면 변수 z와 같은 크기의 벡터 dz가 생성됩니다.
And same story happens when it comes to downstream gradients.
하류 그래디언트에서도 같은 일이 발생합니다.
In downstream gradients-- actually,
하류 그래디언트에서는--
before going to downstream, let me tell you
사실 하류로
a little bit about the local gradients,
가기 전에, x와
where we have gradient of z with respect to x and y.
y에 대한 z의 국소 그래디언트에 대해 조금 말씀드리겠습니다.
And in this case that's the part that I
이 경우, 제가 말한
said there will be Jacobians because now,
부분이 야코비안이 될 것이며, 이제
the gradients will turn into matrices.
그래디언트는 행렬로 변환됩니다.
So we have two Jacobian matrices here
그래서 입력 크기와 출력
defined by the size of their input multiplied
크기를 곱한 두 개의
by the size of the output.
야코비안 행렬이 정의됩니다.
And then this results in downstream gradients
그리고 이것은 상류와 국소 그래디언트의 곱으로
that are multiplication of upstream and the local gradient.
하류 그래디언트를 생성합니다.
And there, we get same size as the inputs x itself.
그곳에서 우리는 입력 x 자체와 같은 크기를 얻습니다.
So we will have a vector again here
그래서 우리는 다시 벡터를 가지게
because the input was a vector, same size,
됩니다. 입력이 벡터였기
in terms of the gradients.
때문에 그래디언트 측면에서 같은 크기입니다.
I just mentioned that gradients of variables with respect
변수의 그래디언트는 항상
to loss always have the same dimensionality
원래 변수와 동일한 차원을
as the original variable itself, as also shown in this slide.
가지며, 이 슬라이드에서도 보여집니다.
So backprop with vectors was this, just one example here.
그래서 벡터로 역전파는 이것이었습니다. 여기 하나의 예입니다.
Let's say we have a function, which is the max of 0 and x.
함수 max(0, x)가 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
That's the ReLU function.
이것이 ReLU 함수입니다.
So this is an element wise function that takes the inputs,
이것은 입력을 받아 0과의 최대값을 취하는 요소별
takes the max between 0.
함수입니다.
And if it's nonzero--
그리고 비제로인
if it's non-negative, it passes through, otherwise
경우-- 비부정적인 경우에는 통과하고, 그렇지
replaces it with a 0.
않으면 0으로 대체합니다.
Assume you get some upstream gradients
상류 그래디언트를 얻었다고 가정하고
and now, we need to build a Jacobian matrix here.
이제 여기에서 야코비안 행렬을 구축해야 합니다.
And this Jacobian matrix, in this case,
이 야코비안 행렬은
because this is an element wise operation,
요소별 연산이기 때문에 다른
it doesn't have any dependence on any of the other inputs, only
입력에 대한 의존성이 없고, 오직 값 자체에
the dependencies on the value itself.
대한 의존성만 있습니다.
This is a very sparse matrix, only has value
이것은 매우 희소한 행렬로, 주
on the main diagonal.
대각선에만 값이 있습니다.
And those values are actually either 0 or 1,
그 값은 실제로 0 또는 1이며,
depending on if the max was actually taken,
최대값이 실제로 취해졌는지,
or a 0 was if the value was passed through,
값이 통과했는지, 아니면
or just the 0 was replaced with it in its place.
0으로 대체되었는지에 따라 다릅니다.
Multiplying it by the upstream gradient
상류 그래디언트와 곱하면
gives us the downstream gradient.
하류 그래디언트를 얻습니다.
And this is how the calculations are done.
그리고 이렇게 계산이 이루어집니다.
As I said, Jacobian here is sparse because in this case,
제가 말했듯이, 여기에서 야코비안은 희소합니다. 왜냐하면 이
the operation is element wise.
경우 연산이 요소별이기 때문입니다.
And that could actually be instead of--
그래서 실제로는 역전파에서
in the backward pass, instead of calculating
그 거대한 희소 야코비안
that huge, sparse Jacobian matrix, what
행렬을 계산하는 대신, 우리는
we do is just use these rule-based calculation
이 최대 함수의 기울기를
of the gradient for this max function.
규칙 기반으로 계산합니다.
So we don't really store that matrix
그래서 우리는 그 행렬을
and do not calculate that because we
저장하지 않고 계산하지 않습니다.
know how the function operates.
함수가 어떻게 작동하는지 알기 때문입니다.
And then this could also be extended
그리고 이것은 행렬과
to matrices and even tensors.
텐서로도 확장될 수 있습니다.
If the inputs are not vectors, they
입력이 벡터가
are high dimensionality data.
아니라면, 그것은 고차원 데이터입니다.
So in those cases, again, the gradients
그래서 그런 경우에는 다시, 변수에
with respect to the variables would
대한 기울기가 해당 특정
be of the same size as that specific variable.
변수와 같은 크기가 될 것입니다.
And calculating the upstream and downstream matrices
상류 및 하류 행렬과 도함수를 계산하는 것은
and derivatives is going to be done same as how we discussed
이전에 벡터에 대해 논의하고 보여준
and showed earlier for vectors.
것과 동일하게 진행됩니다.
And then when it comes to the local gradients, although--
그리고 로컬 기울기에 관해서는, 비록-- 그러나, 출력으로
however, it's going to be a huge matrix, a huge Jacobian
행렬이 있고 입력으로 행렬이 있기 때문에
because we have a matrix as the output
거대한 행렬, 거대한 야코비안이
and the matrix as the input.
될 것입니다.
And then the local gradients will
그리고 로컬
be the same size as the multiplication of its input
기울기는 입력 크기와 출력 크기의 곱과 같은 크기가
size and the output size.
될 것입니다.
So it's going to be a huge matrix by itself.
그래서 그것 자체로도 거대한 행렬이 될 것입니다.
Let me give you an example.
예를 들어 드리겠습니다.
If this is input x and w as input
이것이 입력 x이고 w가 행렬
for a node for a gate with matrix multiplication
곱셈을 위한 노드의 입력으로, y가 출력으로
and generates this y as the output,
생성된다면, y에 대한
calculating derivative of L with respect to y
L의 도함수를 계산하면 이러한
gives us these Jacobian matrices.
야코비안 행렬을 얻습니다.
And say, we have a mini batch size of 64 and dimensionality
그리고 미니 배치 크기가 64이고 이러한 행렬의 차원
of those matrices is 4,096, then this means that,
수가 4,096이라면, 이는 그
that Jacobian matrix, that huge Jacobian matrix will be over 256
거대한 야코비안 행렬이 단일 행렬 곱셈에
gigabytes for just one single matrix multiplication.
대해 256기가바이트가 넘는다는 것을 의미합니다.
So in order to simplify this, what we
그래서 이를 단순화하기 위해, 우리는 값들이 서로에게
do is, we try to look at the values
어떻게 영향을 미치는지
and how they impact each other.
살펴보려고 합니다.
For example, what parts of y will
예를 들어, x의 한 요소가
be affected if one element of x gets impacted?
영향을 받으면 y의 어떤 부분이 영향을 받을까요?
So there, xn and d, this specific one,
그래서 여기서 xn과 d, 이 특정 값은
often affects just one row in the output.
종종 출력의 한 행에만 영향을 미칩니다.
And this basically helps us identify for calculating
그리고 이것은 기본적으로 이러한 각 노드를 계산하는 데
each of these nodes.
도움이 됩니다.
We don't need to create the huge Jacobian.
우리는 그 거대한 야코비안을 만들 필요가 없습니다.
We can actually write the backward pass functions
우리는 사실 행렬 곱셈을 위한 역전파
specifically for matrix multiplication
함수를 더 효율적인 방식으로
in a more efficient way.
작성할 수 있습니다.
And I'm almost done.
그리고 거의 끝났습니다.
So you answer this question.
그래서 이 질문에 답해 보세요.
How much does xn, d affect the value of y and m.
xn, d가 y와 m의 값에 얼마나 영향을 미칩니까?
So this is yn, m that is getting impacts from xn, d.
그래서 이것은 xn, d로부터 영향을 받는 yn, m입니다.
How much does it get impact?
얼마나 영향을 받습니까?
It means that what should I place,
이는 특정 값
or put as its gradient with respect
xn, d에 대한
to the specific value, xn, d?
기울기로 무엇을 배치해야 하는지를 의미합니다.
Just to remind you, this is a multiplication operation.
다시 말씀드리면, 이것은 곱셈 연산입니다.
In multiply gates, it should be a swap.
곱셈 게이트에서는 스왑이 있어야 합니다.
So whatever the answer to this question, is something a value
그래서 이 질문에 대한 답이 W의
in W?
값인가요?
Remember that we had this multiplication gate, which
우리가 스왑 곱셈기인 이 곱셈 게이트를
was a swap multiplier.
가졌던 것을 기억하세요.
So there is a swap happening here.
그래서 여기에서 스왑이 발생하고 있습니다.
So the value of x affecting y, one of the elements in y,
따라서 x가 y에 영향을 미치는 값, y의 요소 중 하나는 x 행렬에 의해
is going to be dependent on the W that
정의된 행 D와 y 행렬에 의해
is in row D defined by the x matrix and column
정의된 열 M에 있는 W에
M defined by the y matrix.
따라 달라집니다.
So it's swapping the values.
그래서 값이 교환되고 있습니다.
It's the same swap.
같은 교환입니다.
But here now, we have to look at the giant matrices
하지만 여기서는 거대한 행렬을 살펴보고
and find which specific element it should be.
어떤 특정 요소여야 하는지 찾아야 합니다.
And then based on that, we can actually
그에 따라 우리는 실제로
replace the entire thing with matrix multiplication and matrix
행렬 곱셈과 행렬 연산으로 전체를 대체할 수
operations.
있습니다.
The gradient of L with respect to x
L의 x에 대한
will be defined as this simple matrix operation.
기울기는 이 간단한 행렬 연산으로 정의됩니다.
And then the gradient of L with respect to W
그리고 L의 W에 대한 기울기는 이
will be defined as this very simple multiplication.
매우 간단한 곱셈으로 정의됩니다.
Again, swap here, for x, we include the entire w.
다시 말해, 여기서 x에 대해 전체 w를 포함합니다.
For w, we include the entire x and do the multiplications.
w에 대해서는 전체 x를 포함하고 곱셈을 수행합니다.
These formulas makes it easy to implement
이 공식들은 더 크고 어려운 연산을
larger and harder operations and get them implemented
구현하기 쉽게 만들어 주며, 역전파에서 구현할
in the backward passes.
수 있게 해줍니다.
All right, we're done.
좋습니다, 우리는 끝났습니다.
Just to summarize, we talked today
요약하자면, 오늘 우리는 완전 연결
about fully connected neural networks.
신경망에 대해 이야기했습니다.
We went through all the steps needed for backpropagation,
우리는 역전파에 필요한 모든 단계, 순전파와 역전파를
the forward passes, backward passes.
살펴보았습니다.
And next session, we will be getting
다음 세션에서는 합성곱 신경망
into the topic of convolutional neural networks.
주제로 들어갈 것입니다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.